JANUARY 1014 AD - OUTSKIRTS
OF GAINSBOROUGH, NORTHEAST ENGLAND
Thorkell's using it as an excuse.
トルケルの方便だ！
That's the only reason I can think of.
他には考えられん！
But, Floki,
し…しかしフローキ様。
-the reports from Derby--
-The left flank is undermanned!
ダービーからの報告では…
左翼が薄いぞ！！
Don't underestimate a force of 500 soldiers.
兵500とて侮るな！
We're talking about Thorkell's army!
相手はトルケル軍だ！
Floki.
フローキ様。
If the reports are true,
報告が事実ならば、
then your actions will be disrespectful.
このなさりようは大変不敬な…
It's impossible.
あり得ぬ！
His Highness Canute can't be alive
and with Thorkell as one of his followers.
あのクヌート殿下がトルケルを従えて生還するなど、
It's impossible!
決してあり得ぬ！
Hey, Floki! Want to fight? I'll fight you.
ようフローキ。戦る気か？相手になるぜ
Restrain yourself, Thorkell.
控えよトルケル
I thought I sent a messenger several days ago
私が帰還する旨、
to notify you of my return, Floki.
数日前に使者を送ったはずだぞ。フローキ
Do you always greet your guests
with spears in hand?
槍をもって出迎えるのが貴様の礼か？
No, of course not...
い…いえ。そのようなことは決して…
Askeladd! Why are you here?
アシェラッド！？なぜ貴様が…！
Are you deaf?
耳が聞こえぬのか貴様
I'm asking you whether you're going
貴様はデンマーク王家に対し…
to draw your bows against a member
of the royal family of Denmark.
弓を引く気かと訊いているのだ
No...
あ…い…いえ、その…
We Jomsvikings received an inaccurate report
わがヨーム戦士団は…
that an enemy army was going to attack...
敵軍襲来との誤報を受けまして…
I apologize.
申し訳ありませぬ…
Notify the king
王陛下の館へ夕刻までに参じると報告しておけ。
that I shall be at his hall by evening.
Make sure you report accurately.
正確にな
What in the world happened?
一体何が…
He's a completely different person.
まるで別人ではないか…！
GAINSBOROUGH CASTLE TOWN
DANISH ARMY HEADQUARTERS
Everyone, listen to me while we walk.
全員歩きながら聞け
We must not strike yet.
今はまだ仕掛けてはならぬ。
CROWN
私の味方はこの軍中に少ない
I don't have many allies within this army.
If we strike now, they'll label us as traitors.
ただ手向かえば反逆者となろう。
We need time to prepare.
手回しの時間が要る。
Thorkell. You betrayed them once,
トルケル。そなたは一度裏切ったが、
but you're still popular among the warriors.
今も戦士たちに人気がある。
Spend time with the leaders
of all the clans
各部族の首領たちと交わり、
and mend ties with them.
関係を修復しておけ
In other words, are you telling me
つまりあれかい？
to go drink as much as I want,
and that you'll pay for it?
アンタのおごりでジャカジャカ酒飲めってこと？
As long as you invite the other leaders.
Now, go.
他の首領を誘ってだぞ。行け
What a wonderful order!
すっっばらしい命令だ！
I'm so glad I decided to follow you.
アンタについてきて正解だったぜ
-Let's go!
-Hey!
行くぞぉ！あっ！おい！
Askeladd. Come with me to see the king.
アシェラッドは私と共に王のところだ。
I want to hear what you think of him.
そなたの人物評を聞きたい
Understood.
はっ
And about the future.
それと今後だ。
How will we achieve it?
いかに事を運ぶ
Understood.
はっ…
I think an assassination would be best
in the short run.
短期的には暗殺がよろしいかと
Your brother, His Highness Harald,
兄王子ハラルド殿下は
is far away in Denmark right now.
This is a good opportunity.
遠くデンマークにいらっしゃいます。これは好機です
If the king passes away right now,
今王陛下が崩御されれば、
then command of the army in England
イングランド方面軍の最高指揮官は
is going to pass to you.
あなた様ということに
However, if we do so, we must hide
the person responsible for it.
この場合…首謀者を偽装する必要がありますが…
Thorfinn.
トルフィン。
In the future, I'll assign you with other tasks
in addition to being a guard.
今後は護衛以外にも働いてもらうことになるだろう。
I'm counting on you.
頼むぞ
Don't give me orders.
命令すんな。
I never said I decided to work for you.
オレァあんたの手下になった覚えはねぇ
Please forgive him for his impertinence.
ご無礼お許し下さい。
I'll make sure I instruct this idiot properly.
このバカへは私から指図しておきます
God...
神は…
must be watching us, even as we stand here now.
こうしている今も、我々を見ていらっしゃるのだろうな
People losing friends,
友を失い、
and parents and children killing each other...
親と子が殺し合う…
He must be looking down on everything
そんな様の全てを、
from up high in heaven.
天空の高みから見下ろしておられるのだろう
I'll never forgive him.
許せぬ
I'm going to create paradise on earth.
私はこの地上に楽土を作るぞ。
A peaceful and prosperous place.
平和で豊かな、
A utopia for those who go through
suffering in their lives.
生きることに苦しむ者たちの理想郷を…
I may not be able to achieve it in one generation,
私の代では成し得ぬかもしれぬ。
but I'm still going to take
それでも最初の一歩を、
the first step.
私が踏み出すのだ
I'm sure that God will cherish me
神はきっと私を愛で、
and summon me to his side.
御許へ召そうとするだろう
But...
だが…
in that moment I will tell him:
その時私はこう言うのだ
"We don't need heaven, nor its trials, any longer.
“もはや天の国も試練も要らぬ。
Our paradise is on earth."
我々の楽土は地上にある”とな
We're going to take back what we lost.
我々が失ったものを取り戻すのだ。
I'm willing to turn into a demon
if that's what it takes to do it.
そのためには…鬼にもなろう
I will help you,
お手伝いいたします。
Your Highness.
殿下
Welcome back.
よくぞ戻った…
I'm glad, Canute.
うれしいぞクヌート
Thank you for your kind words.
ありがたきお言葉。
I lost the soldiers you had entrusted to me.
陛下よりお預かりした兵を失ってしまった。
Your words are more than I deserve.
不肖の身に余ります
Come closer.
近う寄れ
Wait.
お待ち下さい。
What do you think, Thorfinn?
どうだ？トルフィン
Yeah, they're there.
フン。居るな
About 20 of them.
20人ってところか。
There are some up high too. Archers.
高い所にもだ。弓兵だな
Your Highness. It's an ambush.
殿下…伏兵です。
It seems that the king
どうやら王陛下は、
knows about our intentions.
こちらの腹をお察しのようですな
What's wrong? Without further delay, come closer.
どうした？早う寄らぬか
You two.
そなたたち。
You must not draw your swords, no matter what.
何があっても剣を抜いてはならぬぞ。
He who draws his sword first loses.
先に抜いたほうの負けだ。
That's the type of fight this is.
これは…そういうケンカだ
My eyes have gotten used to the darkness.
暗さに目が慣れてきたな。
If I get a little closer,
もう少し近づけば…
I'll be able to see the king's face.
王の顔がわかる。
If I can see his face...
顔を見れば…
Stop.
止まれ
Right there is fine. Kneel down.
そこでよい。ひざまずけ
His eyes are tired.
疲れた眼だ。
Is this who
これが…
the king of the Danes is?
デーン人の王か
Askeladd.
アシェラッド
What happened to Ragnar? I don't see him.
ラグナルはどうした。姿が見えぬが
He died. In Mercia.
死にました。マーシアの地にて
I see. That's too bad.
そうか…それは惜しいな
He was a loyal subject.
あれは誠の忠臣であった。
In normal circumstances, we should be
celebrating your return with food and drink.
本来なら酒肴をもって帰還を祝うべきだが…
However,
一度そなたとは…
I wanted to speak with you once informally.
形式抜きで話をしたいと思うておった
Canute. Only you. Rise.
クヌートのみ立て。
Walk ten steps forward.
10歩前へ進め
You face has changed
ほんのわずかの間に…
in just a short time.
顔がかわったな。
You look like me when I was young.
余の若き日に似ておる
Then
されば…
you must understand what's in my heart.
我が心の内もおわかりでございましょう
You're a troublesome child.
困った子だ…
I never imagined you'd become
そのようなところまで
just like me, even in that regard.
余に似るとは…
Children
子は
grow up watching what their parents do.
親の為し様を見て育つのです。よもや…
Do not blame yourself.
お責めになりますまいな
Long ago, when I was young,
かつて若き日…
I drove my father, the former king, out of this country
余は父である先王を国外へ追い放ち
and seized this crown.
この王冠を奪った。
I did it because I believed it was the best
thing to do for the kingdom.
それが王国のためによき事と信じたからだ。
The former king was cruel, but he was also a coward.
先王は性残忍にして臆病者だった。
The world would sink into chaos if someone
like him had the crown.
そのような者が王冠を戴いては世が乱れる
How can he say that when he's surrounded
by this many guards?
こんだけの護衛に囲まれて何言ってやがる
Shut up. He'll hear you.
黙れ。聞かれるぞ
So, you decided not to keep up the pretense,
Your Highness?
腹芸を使う気はねェってかい、殿下よ…
Don't forget you're surrounded by the enemy.
敵の巣の中にいるってことを忘れなさんなよ…
I thought that I had done something great,
よき事を成した。
and that I could do great things.
よき事を為せると思うておった
Until I put this on, that is.
これをかぶるまではな…
This crown
意志があるのだ。
has its own will.
この王冠にはな
Once you wear this crown, you can command
かぶれば千の船、
a thousand ships and 10,000 men.
万の兵を統率できる。
You can take all kinds of treasure from distant lands.
遠国のあらゆる宝を取り寄せることができる
A power like that of the gods
is bestowed upon you.
神々がごとき力が身に宿る
However...
だが…
However, Canute,
だがクヌートよ。
the king isn't the one who uses that power.
力を使うのは王ではない。
That power is used by the will of the crown.
王冠の意志が使うのだ
Do you mean
王冠が
the crown ordered you...
陛下に命じたというのですか。
to kill me?
私を殺せと
There are only two things that the crown
orders the king to do.
王冠が王に命じるのはただふたつ。
It orders him to use his power,
力を使うことと、
and to increase his power.
力を増やすことだ。
Resistance is futile.
抗うても無駄なことよ。
The crown does not want you.
王冠は、そなたを欲してはおらぬ
Canute.
クヌート。
I'll give you part of Cornwall.
そなたにコーンウォールの一部をやろう
Live your days in peace there
そこで聖書でも読みながら
while reading the Bible.
平穏の日々を送るがよい
If you refuse, then you'll die here.
いやだと申すなら…この場で死ぬがよい
Did the crown make you say that too,
そのお言葉も王冠が言わせているのですか。
-Your Highness?
-Your Highness!
陛下
陛下！
I humbly ask you to let me speak.
おそれながら発言をお許し下さい！
State your name.
名乗れ
I'm Canute's follower,
クヌート様の従士。
Askeladd, son of Olaf.
ウォラフの子、アシェラッドと申します
With all due respect, consider whether your actions
are in line with the will of the crown.
失礼ながら、果たしてこの御沙汰は王冠の意志にかないましょうや！？
Continue.
続けよ…
His Highness Canute
王子殿下は
stole Thorkell and the military power he commands
away from London.
ロンドンよりトルケルという戦力を奪い取りました
If you become the king of England,
陛下がイングランド王にご即位なされれば…
then London will have no choice but to surrender.
彼の町には降伏より他、道はありませぬ
The wealth of London will become yours untouched,
Your Highness.
ロンドンの富は、無傷のまま陛下のものとなります
His Highness Canute
多大なる犠牲を払い、
is the one who made the sacrifice
この戦果をもたらしたるは
for this great achievement.
クヌート殿下に他なりません
Is it not unreasonable to punish the man who rendered
such distinguished service?
功労ある者が罰せられる道理がありましょうか。
Your handling of this matter
この御沙汰…
would deeply trouble
新たな領地の割譲において、
your generals when the time comes
to divide the new territory.
各将軍に動揺を与えます
Please reconsider this matter.
何卒…ご再考を！
You're a man who's good with words.
口のまわる男だ。
Askeladd. "The one covered in ashes"?
アシェラッド…“灰まみれ”か…
That's your nickname.
それはあだ名であろう。
Tell me the name that your father gave you.
貴様の父が授けた名を申せ
I'm only known as Askeladd.
ただ…アシェラッドと。
My father didn't give me a name.
父は私に名を与えませんでした
You must be the child of one of his mistresses. No...
妾の子か…いや…
You must be a child he forced one of his slaves to have.
奴隷に産ませた子かの？
What's going on?
I've never seen Askeladd get so mad.
なんだ！？アシェラッドがここまで怒るなんて…
Canute.
クヌート…
You have a good follower.
よい従士を持っておるな。
It is just as he said.
そやつの申すとおりだ
I have to reward you.
そなたたちには褒美をやらねばならんな
I am leaving for York tomorrow.
余は明日ヨークに発つ。
There, I shall throw a banquet.
彼の地にて宴席を設ける
I shall give you your reward there.
褒美はそこで授けよう
My blood froze just now, Your Highness.
肝を冷やしましたぞ殿下
What are you so worried about?
何を慌てることがある
As you already know, the king
そなたの察するとおり…王には今、
doesn't have enough justification to kill me right now.
私を殺すだけの大義名分がない
He's the man who they call the wise king.
賢王と呼ばれたいお方なのだ。
As long as we don't do anything reckless,
こちらさえ軽挙に出ねば、
it's safer to lie within the king's bosom.
王の内懐はむしろ安全だろう
Then that's all the more reason to refrain from
provoking him like you did just now.
ではなおのこと先ほどのような挑発はお控え下さい
It's nothing of consequence.
なんのことはない。
King Sweyn is a slave to the crown.
スヴェン王は王冠の奴隷というわけだ。
The power of the crown.
王冠の力…
I will show him how to use it.
私が使いこなしてみせようぞ
Askeladd...
アシェラッドか…
I must be wary of him.
少々警戒せねばならんな…
Cheers!
カンパーイ！
All right! Don't be shy!
さあ！ジャンジャンやってくれ！
This is all on His Highness Canute!
全部クヌート殿下のおごりだぜ！！
Long live the prince!
殿下バンザーイ！
-That's his 57th glass!
-He's a monster!
57杯目だ！
バケモンだコイツー！
Hey! You've been drinking a lot. Who are you?
おーい！さっきからガブガブガブガブ飲みやがって。誰だおめェは？
I don't remember inviting you here.
坊主なんざ招いた覚えねーぞ？
I'm Willibald. Did you forget me?
私はヴィリバルドです。お忘れですか？
What?
は？
いーっ！？
-Your beard is gone!
-You look so young. How old are you?
あのヒゲの！？
若いな！いくつだよ！
I'm 23.
23です
-No way!
-You're in your early 20s?
うそだろ！？
20代前半！？
All right! It's my turn next!
よーし！次はオレが相手だ！
The captain is up now!
大将のお出ましだ！
You're behind by 58 glasses!
ハンデ58杯っすよ！
What a strange man.
不思議な男だ。
He does whatever he wants,
but no one hates him.
好き放題に生きながら、周りの者に憎まれぬ
True.
はァ
So? What do you think?
で…どうだ。
Do you think you can kill him? The king?
殺れそうか？あの王を
It's going to be difficult.
難しい…
That's what I'd say.
と言わざるを得ませんな
I got the impression he's a smart man.
頭の良いお方とお見受けしました。
He's discerning, and he's a man of action
who can make the first move.
洞察力と先手を打つ行動力をお持ちです。
When he saw that we wouldn't buckle under his threats,
he switched to a different strategy.
我々が脅しに屈さぬと見るや、次の手に転ずるあたり…
I would say he's skilled in war.
戦上手とも申せましょう
No wonder he's the king of the country.
さすがは一国の王、といったところでしょうか。
He's a tough opponent.
手強いですぜ
Even if we're planning to kill him someday,
I guess now's not the time.
いずれ殺すにしても今ではない…か
Let's submit to his wishes for the time being
ま。当分は王陛下のスキを窺いつつ、
while we wait for our chance.
恭順の体でいきましょう
Your Highness! Your Highness!
殿下！殿下！
I'm so glad you returned safely!
無事のご帰還、お喜び申し上げます！
Do you have any idea how much I, Gunnar,
worried about you?
このグンナル、どれほどに心配したことか！
I apologize that I was unable to greet you at the castle.
ご入城にお出迎えもせず、申し訳ございません。
I just returned from a foreign country.
なにぶんたった今！異国より帰って参ったものですから。
I always believed you'd return, of course!
もちろん、きっとのご生還信じておりましたぞ！おや、
Oh, is this gentleman over here your new follower?
こちらの御仁は新しい従士殿でございますか？
Can you introduce me?
ご紹介頂けますかな？
This is Ragnar's brother, Gunnar.
Please become acquainted with each other.
ラグナルの弟、グンナルだ。見知りおけ
I'm Askeladd, son of Olaf.
ウォラフの子、アシェラッドと申します
Oh, you look like a dependable character.
ほぉ！なんとも頼もしい風格ですな。
I'm Gunnar.
グンナルと申す
By the way, Your Highness...
ところで殿下…
that plan from a long time ago...
The prospects look brighter now.
かねてよりの計画…メドが立ち申した。
I'm talking about the Duchy of Normandy.
ノルマンディー公国です。
I wanted to talk to you about it later
with my brother.
その件について、兄も交えて後ほど…
Ragnar is dead.
ラグナルは死んだ
Sorry for making you go through all that trouble.
私のためにすまぬことをしたな
And I'm not going to go into exile.
それから…亡命はせぬ
-Your Highness? What did you say?
-I'm sorry
殿下…なんと申された…
そなたが諸国を奔走してくれていたことは大儀であった。
to put you to the trouble of
running around to the other countries.
I just picked a fight with King Sweyn.
先ほどスヴェン王にはケンカを売ってきた。
-Please help me.
-My brother...
そなたも力を貸せ
あ、兄者が…
Gunnar.
グンナル
Your job is to keep an eye on the king
and report back to me.
そなたの仕事は、王の監視と報告だ。
Choose soldiers who you trust.
使う兵は信用できる者を選べ
Your Highness! You must not talk about that
in a place like this!
殿下！そっ…そのような話を、こんな所で…！
I don't care. This is actually a good place
to talk in secret.
かまわぬ。むしろこの場は密談によい
Your Highness...
殿下…
You've changed.
お変わりになられた…
Of course I've changed.
I must change everything.
変わるさ。全てを変えてゆかねばならぬ
Gunnar's no good.
あのグンナルってのはいかんなァ。
I don't think he's as loyal to the prince
as he says.
口ほど殿下への忠心があるとも思えんし…
How wonderful that you're so devoted
to staying prepared.
予習復習に余念のないことで。
Doesn't your right arm hurt?
右腕、痛くないのかねェ？
-Askeladd.
-What?
アシェラッド
あ？
I see. You're going home?
そうか…故郷に帰るか
I know you said you don't care,
アンタは気にしねェと言ってくれたけど…
but we did betray you.
やっぱオレたちゃ裏切り者だし…
I don't know how I can face you anymore--
Ouch!
なんつーか…この先どのツラして会やいいのか…
痛で！
I got you!
当たった～！ハハハッ！
And look what happened to my brother.
なんか…兄者もあんなんなっちまったし…
I hope Bjorn's wounds heal.
ビョルンの傷…治るといいな…
Atli! And you still call yourself a Viking?
アトリ。おめェそれでもヴァイキングかよ？
I can't believe I had such an honest man working for me.
よくもまァこんな真人間がオレの手下になったもんだぜ
Bjorn's not going to last long.
ビョルンは長くもたねェよ。
The wound reached his intestines.
傷がはらわたまで達してる
Now,
これでもう
Thorfinn is the only one left from among my men.
昔からの手下はトルフィンだけってことになるな。
It's the perfect time for making a fresh start.
再出発にゃちょうどいい
A bracelet?
腕輪？
It's gold. Take it.
金だ。持ってけ
What? I don't need it! There's no reason for me to take it.
えぇ！？いっ、いらねェよ！もらう理由がねェ！
Just take it.
いいから受け取れ。
There's no such thing as having too much money
while traveling.
路銀が多くて困るこたァねェだろが
Sorry. I appreciate it.
sすまねェ…じゃあ…ありがたく…ん？
What?
あれ？
Hey! Are you going to give it to me or not?
なんだよ！？くれんのかくれねェのかどっちだよ！？
I have one condition.
条件がある
Never pick up a sword ever again.
二度と剣を握るな。
Swords don't suit you, Atli.
おめェにゃ似合わねェ。アトリ
Raise some sheep, get a wife,
羊を飼い嫁をもらって
have a kid, and die in your bed.
ガキをこさえてベッドで死ね
If I see you on the battlefield in the future,
I'm going to kill you,
これから先、おめェを戦場で見かけた時は…
even if you're on my side.
味方でも斬るぞ
Okay. I understand.
あァ…わかった
-What's that?
-This?
それなに？
ん？これか？
It's something important.
こりゃあ大切な…
It's pretty.
That's too expensive! Give me a discount.
高ェよ！まけろ！
Show me some younger women!
もっと若い女出せよ若い女ァ！
-Bring the younger women!
-Any takers?
FEBRUARY 1014 AD - YORK, DANISH
ARMY-OCCUPIED TOWN, NORTHUMBRIA REGION